These German children are in their
garden reenacting a war that they were
far too young to have taken part in.
They were born in 1900 and the First
World War had planted in their hearts
the bitter seed of grief and defeat.
Some of them would later become [music]
the driving force of the Nazi party. And
to impose their vision of a renewed
Germany, they would [music] attack the
law and pervert its rules.
>> The law is a weapon that the Nazis
turned to in order to take Germany and
its society by storm.
>> A weapon for the self-defense of the
race. That was the law for the Nazis.
The individual disappeared as a subject
of the law and was replaced by the
community of the people.
[music]
Smoke.
There are thousands of sounds, images,
[music] and documents. All the pieces of
this puzzle must be assembled to see how
law [music] and justice became the
weapons of a crime.
At the heart of Hitler's courts, lawyers
and magistrates would play their part in
a pitilous war to bring to heal the
judicial [music] system.
Some remarkable destinies shed light on
this story.
Lilo Khnitzki, a committed young lawyer
and pioneer in a profession which was
until then reserved for men, but also
Verer Best, lawyer and Nazi. Johan
Reichart, last in a famous line of
Munich executioners, [music]
and Hans Littton, barristister,
Democrat.
In 1931, One affair revealed to everyone
that the law was a vital issue for the
Nazis.
From the beginning of the 1920s, Adolf
Hitler's Nazi party was defying the
courts and the institutions.
In the streets, [music] their militia,
the Stormtroopers, or the SA, were
beating up and murdering opponents, and
communists in particular.
They openly defied the young VHimar
Republic.
Many of them were accused of acts of
political violence and sent for trial.
And over 8 years, the Nazi party were
the object in almost 2,000 court cases.
But the trial that opened on the 8th of
May 1931 stunned the whole of Germany.
For this time, Hitler himself was
summoned.
the leader of the extreme right in
court. Excitement gripped the streets of
Berlin in the [music] warm spring of
1931.
The instigator of this earthquake was a
young barristister,
Hans Littton. He was 27 and familiar
with cases against the Nazis.
For this new trial, he had decided to
prove that Hitler was a threat to the
[music] system.
Stormtroopers had fired at some
communists in a Berlin dance hall, a
run-of-the-mill case.
But this time, Hans Littton was
determined to [music] make life
difficult for Hitler.
Eight months previously, Hitler had
taken an oath [music] before the
tribunal of the rich in Lifick, and he
had sworn to respect the law and never
have recourse to violence.
For Litton, it was a simple calculation.
Prove that Hitler, as head of the party,
was responsible for the atrocities
committed by the SA. To everyone's
astonishment, the young barristister
issued a summon against Hitler and
called him as a witness.
In room 664, Hans Littton was ready. He
held a document signed by Joseph
Gubbles,
head of propaganda and loyal to Hitler.
>> In this brochure, Nazi,
Joseph Gerbles laid down guidelines for
militants on how they should behave.
It was written,
"All we wish to do is free Germany,
nothing more. If the people do not want
to be freed, we do not care. We will do
it without their consent."
Further on, it says, "The will to be in
power creates the means needed for that
power."
During the hearing, Hans Littton
confronted Hitler with his statements.
Hitler knew that he was cornered and it
showed.
He finally had to distance himself from
Gerbles, declaring
that text has not been authorized by the
party.
In the end, he was yelling and screaming
in the chamber. What right did Litton
have to dare ask him these questions? He
shouted that the party respected the law
and would always do so.
At 1809, Hitler's court appearance
ended.
Would the question of perjury be raised?
The verdict would come in 10 days.
But Hitler's rage had caused a scandal
and he had to be called to order.
In Germany, [music] law courts are also
temples
and Hitler had just blasphemed.
Germany held its breath [music] as it
awaited the verdict. And even more so
did Lilo Kaznitzki, the young democratic
lawyer.
She had followed the details of the
[music] trial with her journalist
brother. Hans Littton was her friend at
university and he was defending the
democracy that she believed in.
To learn more about Lilo, you have to go
to the Jewish Museum in Berlin.
That's where her file is kept in the
silence of the archives,
row two, box 229.
Lilo's real name was Elizabeth. She was
the eldest daughter of Martin Kuznitzki,
a doctor of Polish origin who was Jewish
on his mother's side,
>> and Elizabeth Lilian, a Protestant from
Denmark.
>> The family was certainly quite well
known in Cologne. Lilo had grown up in
an educated and cultivated family.
After attending a Protestant school for
girls, she took her balora, which was
fairly unusual. She then decided to go
on to university.
>> Like Hans Littton, Lilo belonged to the
stratum of young people that VHimar had
fostered by encouraging many of them to
go to university so as to rebuild the
elite decimated by the Great War.
For Lilo, Vhimar also meant women's
right to vote. And like many other young
women, she was emancipated, smoking,
sometimes wearing men's clothes, going
out alone, and making love as she
wanted.
Lilo was happy in this free and tolerant
world. She wanted it. She defended it.
That's why she wanted to be a lawyer.
She didn't merely study, she also got a
doctorate.
And in 1927, she also obtained a first
job at the regional tribunal in Cologne,
convinced that at the heart of the
democracy of the VHimar Republic, she
would be able to fight for justice.
>> Kimhan,
>> it was this democracy she loved so much
that the Nazis were threatening and she
understood the risks that Hans Littton
was running.
From the start of the trial, he was
pursued by the hatred of militant Nazis
and was no longer safe in the street.
Hitler himself, while waiting to know
what the political consequences of this
affair would be, had to face ridicule.
During his court appearance, a young
photographer called Leo Rosenthal took
this photo.
Hastily taken, it is a little blurred,
but it captures Hitler's panic as he
faced Littton. [clears throat]
He is stunned, dazed by the
confrontation.
The photo immortalizes his collapse.
Hitler would never forget Hans Littton.
Especially
as the day after the trial, the
Democratic press was not slow to rub
salt into the wound. The press recounted
Hitler's agony. How for more than 3
[music] hours, Litton inflicted on him a
pitilous interrogation.
How he put his finger on Hitler's
contradictions one by one. How Hitler
got himself in a tangle, was furious,
[music] lost his temper.
And yet the verdict finally delivered by
the tribunal was very lenient. The front
pages of the newspapers announced only
very mild punishments for the thugs of
the SA and for Hitler, no further
action.
The editorials considered it a political
verdict that showed the benevolence of
the conservative judges [music]
regarding the head of the Nazi party.
Barely a few days after this resounding
[music] trial, quite a different event
gripped the public.
At the UFA Palat Cinema in Berlin, the
filmmaker Fritz Lang's new film M the
Cursed, often known simply as M, had its
opening night.
>> In this film, an elusive killer is
terrorizing a town.
>> As they discovered the plot, Berliners
got a strange feeling.
Fritz Lang's M is basically a film that
shows the Nazi counter society. The
underworld, the mob, crooks, the
criminals portrayed in the film are
clearly a metaphor for the Nazi
organization which appears in the film
as a criminal organization. It shows the
incompetence, mismanagement or
inefficiency of traditional institutions
and it's also clearly a film about the
Nazi conception of the law which is
debated at the end.
>> In the script, the underworld and the
common people capture the killer and
organize a secret trial.
This kangaroo court challenged the
system.
It rejected official justice and imposed
its own idea of law exactly the way the
Nazis did [music] in real life.
The film was an instant success and
without doubt Fritz Lang savored it,
[music] remembering that the original
title was Killers in Our Midst.
Even though M the Cursed is a piece of
cinema, Fritz Lang's imagination was
born of grim reality.
In the autumn of 1931, a new affair
burst onto the scene. And once again,
the leader of the Nazi party was center
stage.
A few months earlier, when Hitler was
battling with Hans Littton, a young
overzealous Nazi militant was drawing up
plans for a coup d'eta [music] in the
event of a communist threat.
His name was Verer Best.
and he was a very younglooking and
brilliant lawyer.
And after his law thesis, he joined the
NSDAP, [music] the Nazi party, with the
number 341338.
An anti-semite and ideologically close
to the extreme right, he belonged to the
radical and nationalist youth that was
gradually taking over in the
universities.
Once his studies were completed, this
young militant became an associate judge
in his native region of Hessa.
After his day's [music] work in the
solitude of his office, he had drawn up
a plan for a coup d'eta.
In autumn 1931, this document was leaked
to the press under the title The Boxheim
Papers. It immediately caused a scandal.
A few days later, on the way to Munich
for the meeting, Verbess was shaking in
his boots.
He could think of nothing worse for this
first meeting with Hitler. He knew he
had to put his party in a very delicate
position just before the elections.
Best was conducted into Hitler's office.
And when he was finally face to face
with the furer, nothing happened as he
had imagined.
>> For Hitler, even if a tactical error had
been committed, best conformed to most
of the normative criteria that befitted
a state activist. And that was exactly
the kind of attitude that Hitler hoped
and prayed for.
And so in fact, Hitler had to reprimand
the young national socialist at the
beginning, telling him, "Listen, old
boy, you could have saved us having that
image. But when it comes down to it,
that's how you have to carry on."
Better still, while Best was struggling
and some members [music] of the party
demanded that he be thrown out, Hitler
came publicly to his rescue.
Surprising benevolence indeed,
especially as everyone knew Hitler's
contempt for lawyers, as this phrase
related by his followers shows,
it used to be actors they buried in the
communal grave.
Nowadays, they should bury lawyers
there.
Hitler clearly had a social and
intellectual complex with regard to
anyone who had an education and
especially lawyers. Basically to loa the
lawyers in Germany was rather equivalent
to rejecting or criticizing technocrats
in France. It's roughly the same.
Indeed, in his great moments of
demagoguy in his speeches to workers,
Hitler said, "I am one of you.
Historically,
[cheering]
lawyers and the law have always held an
important place in the German system.
There is a special place for the
training of lawyers in Germany. A unique
training that also gives the opportunity
to exceed to the highest levels in
politics, to the highest ranks in the
civil service. The law is one of the
royal roots.
Lawyers therefore are among those elite
people who are never far from power. So
despite the contempt he felt for them,
Hitler understood very early on that he
had to count on that body of people.
The rising generation in the
universities like Verer Best were
radical
and despite the aversion they felt at
first for the populism of [music] the
Nazis, these young people gradually
joined and became the majority in the
student bodies.
This nationalistic [music]
and anti-semitic youth was an ideal
hunting ground for the party of the
swastika.
At the end of the 1920s, those people
were at the end of their studies and
faced a future of unemployment with the
crisis of 1929.
And that is when schemes for canvasing
young doctors appeared, notably young
doctors of law to encourage them to join
the party. Not only so that they would
have a status, mission, a job, but
better still to open the possibility of
an absolutely marvelous career.
When he joined the NSDAP, Verbest was
hoping to play a role in politics.
And that was where the Boxheim affair
ruined everything. It even cost him his
post as a judge.
But at the same time, Best had just had
a crucial encounter, the SS.
This was Hitler's bodyguard, handpicked
Nazis, radical and committed to embody
the elite of the future thousand-year
Reich.
Their leader was Hinrich Himmler and he
had spotted Verer Best.
So it was with a new number 23377
that Best put on his SS uniform.
The SS recruited three types of people.
The first type were lawyers, second type
managers and engineers, and the third
type specialists in social sciences.
Together they could combine political
radicalism, academic excellence, and
bureaucratic efficiency. And at the same
time, they recruited people who mostly
made up a functioning elite, which
enabled the SS to penetrate the state
institutions, either local or federal,
of German society.
In the summer of 1932, the economic
situation was not good.
One German and three was out of work.
[music] Among them was Johan Reichart.
He was the last in a line of
executioners who had formerly been
wealthy. Like many of his countrymen, he
had now fallen on hard times.
>> There were relatively few executions
under the Vimar Republic. So he had to
find other ways to feed his family.
Thus he was for a time an inkeeper. Then
he sold religious pamphlets around the
villages.
Then finally he went and settled in the
Netherlands to sell vegetables.
When an execution was planned, they sent
him a telegram from Bavaria.
He then had to go to Munich to carry out
his work as an executioner.
He always arrived on time.
July 10th, 1932. In the train that took
him back to Munich, Johan Reichard was
doing some thinking. Since he had been
living in the Netherlands, it was only
the second time he had been called on to
officiate his executioner.
This time it was a woman, a first for
him.
After the execution, Reichard went into
town for a few beers with his
associates. They confirmed that the
atmosphere had changed since he left.
And as the elections drew near, it
became more like a climate of civil
[music] war.
So he was fairly relaxed about taking
the train back to Holland.
There, his wife and three children were
waiting for him in their small Amsterdam
flat.
2 weeks later, he learned the results of
the elections.
With 37.3% of the votes far ahead of the
Social Democrats, the Nazi party became
the country's first party.
In Germany, the news was like a
bombshell.
However, long months of negotiations
were needed before at last, on January
30th, 1933, Marshall Hindenburg agreed
to appoint Hitler as Chancellor.
On this day, January 30th, 1933, Lilo's
father, Martin Kaznitzki, read the news
in the morning paper.
The appointment of Hitler to the post of
chancellor foreshadowed dark days to
come.
Nevertheless, the Kiskis decided to go
off on holiday to the mountains.
After all, the democratic press
recognized the legality of the process
that had brought Hitler to power.
And then, although he had to appoint
Hitler, old Marshall Hindenburg [music]
was still president of the country.
He was a hero of the Great War, and his
presence was comforting.
There were only three [music] Nazis in
the right-wing coalition.
Yet the lawyer Wilhelm Frrick became
home secretary
and Guring was made prime minister of
Prussia, the biggest of the German
regions. These were key posts for
controlling the police.
To contain the Nazis, Hindenburg named
his ally, the conservative France von
Poppin, as vice chancellor.
He was a political veteran and was
supposed to keep the situation under
control. But would he be up to it?
Some, like Lilo, were worried about the
trivialization of the Nazis [music]
discourse,
and Hitler traveled up and down the
country, using his newfound legitimacy
as a formidable megaphone.
Fore
in the prime and that is a file.
UNDER THE NATURAL
ON THE TOUCHES OR THE TOUCHES RIGHT
I [screaming]
SEE C
>> [music]
>> AFTER. After the fire in the rice stag,
Germany was in a state of shock.
The convenient arrest of a communist
suspect allowed the Nazis to wave the
threat of a plot.
Immediately, Hitler got Hindenburg to
put a signature to an exceptional
measure.
In the morning of the fire in the
Reichstag on the 28th of February 1933,
an order was signed by Hindenburg, an
order for the protection of the people
and the state, conferring almost
unlimited powers on the executive, on
the government, and that's to say on the
police.
Straight away, the Nazis began a wave of
arrests.
Hans Littton, the lawyer who had
ridiculed Hitler a year and a half
earlier, was sound asleep when someone
violently [music] hammered on his door.
Hitler had not forgotten him.
His name was among the first on the
list. He was taken immediately to
Spandow prison.
The arrest went on for several days.
Dozens of other notables soon joined
Hans Littton behind bars.
members of parliament, journalists,
intellectuals, or writers, most of them
opposed to the Nazis.
Totally dumbfounded, Hans Linton watched
the rules of the legal system being
sabotaged.
>> In other words, as from 28th of February
1933, people in Germany were no longer
in a state governed by the law.
There was no legal control. You could be
arrested, placed in custody in a
concentration camp without motive for an
indeterminate time, undefended, and
beyond the control of the judiciary.
>> Soon, Hans Littton was transferred to a
camp at Sonnenberg.
The guards at the camp were members of
the SA and wore the armbands of
auxiliary police.
This proved that between the usual
members of the judiciary and the
arbitrary Nazi policemen, any
distinction was suddenly blurred.
>> Verer Best, now legal consultant in the
SS, was now one of those given the task
of [music] establishing the legal
framework for these arrests.
And thanks to him, as with the arrest
[music] of Hans Littton, the police
always turned up with an authoritative
document.
The Shutzh
was a tool invented before the Nazis
came to power.
But Verer Best belonged to that amalgam
of policeman/ lawyer/smilitant
that brought it up to date, rewrote it
and brought it into the legal and
administrative arsenal of the Third
Reich.
We can see it in the letterhead,
the state secret police. It was a police
decision, but the paper was mauve
because the color mauve was the color
for legal decisions, judicial decisions.
In other words, the issue was
deliberately obfiscated and a
legitimized form was given to a purely
police decision by making it seem to be
a judicial decision. So there was no
control by a judge. There was no longer
any respect for basic freedoms.
The Nazis were to cross another decisive
line only 3 [music] weeks after having
put an end to fundamental rights and
individual liberties.
There reigned [music] a climate of
intimidation backed by the massive
presence of the SA when on March 23rd
the first meeting of the new parliament
was held.
Supported by the new exceptional
measures, Hitler commanded the MPs to
accord him full powers.
>> [music]
>> The next morning on March 24th, the law
was passed [music] by 444 votes to 94.
From then on, Hitler governed alone.
Without having touched the Constitution,
he had set up a dictatorship.
The funeral
is the rightandch.
forts mansk
>> but what community was Frick referring
to and who among the German people could
still claim to belong to it
you could only be in the community if
you were of the German race of German
blood the essential corollery of
community in the Nazi sense
there are other types of community race
obviously
and it was also being in what the Nazis
came to call the Fura's geol shaft.
The geol shaft was that group that
followed the furer, the chief with
unconditional obedience, with an
absolute loyalty.
NEED
FOR
TITAN.
[cheering]
>> It's hard to imagine today this
invisible dangerous frontier.
colleagues and neighbors who were
familiar to them, the friends they
openly confided in. Never again would
the Germans be able to look at them in
the same way.
In the Berlin Jewish Museum, you can
find evidence of the day when Lilo
Kaznitzki discovered that she was on the
wrong side of that invisible line.
On the morning of April 3rd, the police
came to the family home. As it happened,
she was not there and it was Martin
Kitzki, Lilo's father, who opened the
door.
>> The policeman said, "I want your
daughter's passport." Martin Khnitzki
was busy and paid little attention to
the policeman.
The policeman made this a pretext for
lodging a complaint for defamation.
He was being somewhat overzealous.
1 M13033
was the number of the file that
Inspector [music] Young immediately
opened against Martin Kitki for some
obscure motive.
>> The only thing that could possibly
explain that was that Elizabeth or Lilo
Kaznitzki was probably politically
committed and consequently was in the
sights of the authorities and therefore
the police.
As from the 30th of January 1933,
there was a policy that the Nazis called
the glyon that could be translated by
bringing to heal but which means
indexing, synchronizing, putting to one
side in short centralization,
rationalization, purggation and as it
happened the legal world was rapidly
purged by the law of 7th of April 1933.
This was a law that affected the civil
service and which stipulated that all
friends of the national union
government, thus people on the left,
were excluded from the civil service.
Moreover, the Jews had an exemption
starting with war veterans, but that was
soon done away with.
The associations of solicitors and of
lawyers followed very swiftly without
being consulted or with the friendly
suggestion that they should take notice
of this law. In other words, that what
applied to the civil service would also
apply to lawyers, solicitors, etc.
And therefore there would be a host of
professional bans laid down sometimes
violently since at the judiciary
tribunal of Berlin essay troops had
burst in and violently thrown out the
judges and lawyers they considered to be
on the left or Jewish
or worse still both
altogether. together. There were
thousands of lawyers, solicitors, and
magistrates who were sacked or forbidden
to practice.
In Prussia, Guring alone, [music] since
he was now prime minister, dismissed 28%
of top civil servants.
Other victims of the purge were
university professors of law.
Carl Schmidt, [music] then considered to
be the greatest legal mind, approved.
And on May 1st, he joined the Nazi
party. As for Lilo, a lawyer from a
half-Jewish family and political
activist, she became a target.
But she wasn't yet caught up in the
purge. And unlike the 38,000 people who
were already leaving Germany, she stayed
in the country.
Fritz Lang chose to leave with the first
wave of immigrants.
And though he chose exile, he saw the
dark institutions of his film M the
Cursed become reality.
In just a few months, an avalanche of
laws and decrees descended on Germany.
The Nazi plan was taking shape and
Hitler did not act alone.
After Guring, who was extending his
powers, after Frick at the interior
ministry, other loyal followers saw
their powers increase. Gibbles at the
propaganda ministry, R at the head of
the SA, Himmler in charge of the SS and
the Bavarian police. To comfort public
opinion and the political class, the
conservative France Girtner was left in
his post as Minister of Justice.
But in Hitler's wake came a number of
Nazis who had been loyal from the very
beginning.
In particular, Hans Frank, Hitler's
former lawyer,
and Roland Frysler, Secretary of State
in Prussia and one of the most radical
ideologues.
For them, above all, Frysler, the law
and justice [music] were weapons to be
used in the internal war against the
enemies of the German nation and the
German race.
If the law is a weapon, you need
soldiers. Roland Frysler called them the
armored divisions of the law, a warlike
term that mainly applied to the young
generation of lawyers.
Hundreds of law students about to get
their degrees took the trains to
Utubberg, 90 km south of Berlin.
>> There, in a camp where they would spend
8 weeks, these future lawyers and public
prosecutors underwent a physical and
ideological retraining,
all under the supervision of Roland
Frysler.
for
the mind
and camarader.
Community camaraderie. Indoctrination
begins with the repetition of these
ideas. In a book that he would soon
write in exile, the young lawyer
Sebastian Hafner recounts the effects of
this brainwashing.
If several weeks in Udeg,
it was the work of camaraderie.
Camaraderie annihilates the feeling of
personal responsibility.
That's what ideological education really
was.
By agreeing to take part in the game
they were playing with us, we were
turning ourselves automatically into, if
not Nazis, [music] at least into a
material the Nazis could use.
The armored divisions of the law. Unlike
Sebastian Hafner, most of these young
people quite frivolously agreed to
become the spearhead
for most of them belong to a radical
generation coming out of the
universities.
So swastikas and patriotic songs
replaced the togas and books of legal
proceedings. In this archive film, they
have just symbolically condemned and
hanged a representation of a paragraph
symbol, a sacrilege that was both a bit
of fun and heavy with meaning.
In Germany, the laws are more often
subdivided into paragraphs and less into
articles as they do in France. So when
you target the paragraph, you are
targeting the way in which the laws are
subdivided and therefore the formal
conception of the law.
Before 1933 in Germany, we had a system
of liberal law as in the whole of Europe
and the west. That is where everything
stems from the individual. Everything
starts with the dignity of the
individual, his freedoms and the
protecting of his dignity and freedoms.
With the Nazis, this concept was
reversed and it was decided that
henceforward the basis of law was no
longer the individual but the community
of the people.
Symbolically to produce a paragraph
wasn't enough to radically and durably
reverse practices. It was necessary to
discipline and control the legal
professions.
Created by the Nazis and presided over
by Hans Franc, the Academy of Law would
take care of it.
>> In 1933, Hans Franc was brought into the
government as commissioner of the Reich
for bringing into line both the legal
establishment and judicial associations.
That was the first thing. Another factor
perhaps was the presidency of the
academy for German law.
Hans Fran would preside over this
academy from 1933 to 1942.
To all appearances, it was a standard
law academy. Its brief was to train
lawyers, support judicial publications,
prepare legal bills. But all these
functions of a law academy and in this
case the academy for German law took on
a special meaning since it required
specifically bringing into line and
breathing life into a new ideology.
>> Within the academy there were eminent
law professors like Carl Schmidt,
philosophers such as Martin Haidiger,
future magistrates [music] and lawyers
and of course Roland Frysler.
There were also people with no judicial
qualifications [music] appointed just
out of political expediency,
industrialists or well-known
personalities.
Hans Franc
decided to set the example.
On the ground, magistrates saw a part of
their prerogatives brought into
question.
Some of them openly complained.
In the personal file of prosecutor
Reutder, there are dozens of notes that
this conservative civil servant had
addressed to the government minister
denouncing the interference of the state
secret police, the Gestapo. In many
cases,
procedures, illegal interrogations,
repeated irregularities for offenses of
a political nature, non-transmission of
information to the public prosecutor's
office, and even sometimes the
disappearance of proof.
In concrete terms, a defendant can be
transferred before a repressive penal
tribunal and find him or herself at the
end of the proceedings acquitted and
walk out of the court. And the Gustapo
might grab him saying, "Yes, all right,
but we've got other things against you."
In any case, you're outside the
community.
In this pitilous war against the enemies
of the community, the independence of
judges was under threat everywhere. In
the Colong Tribunal where she worked,
Lilo Kuznitzki saw it every day.
To reach the ideal of justice for the
community of the people that they
dreamed of, the Nazis had set out to
defeat the judicial [music] system.
Whether it was birthright citizenship,
health, heredity, or politics, special
tribunals were created to sanction
[music] new offenses defined by Nazi
dogma.
>> Every time there was a problem, they
created a law and then a tribunal.
So there were tribunals in every field
and especially there was an interesting
tribunal which concerned the handing
down of hereditary farms.
Because there are two German key words,
blood and landlord.
The German peasant was in Nazi minds the
essence of national socialism.
So what was important was that great
property should be passed down. If
someone were Jewish, he had no right to
own land. If someone were enough of a
congenital idiot, he had no right to own
land and so on. Every possible exclusion
was invented to preserve the purity of
the race, so to speak. It was land
tenure that brought honor to German
soil.
>> Special tribunals, Gustapo, and the
police [music] became the instruments of
this bringing into line that the Nazis
called synchronization, and nothing must
stop it, even if it meant getting around
traditional justice.
It was a vast movement that also
transformed the life of executioner
Johan Reichart. In June 1933, after two
years in Holland, he came back and
settled in Munich with his family.
He had just been offered a long-term
contract. It was beyond his wildest
dreams. The Richarts could once again
enjoy the Munich summer and swimming in
the canal, a carefree happiness they had
almost forgotten.
An income of 3,000 marks a month, a
small fortune.
All things were possible again thanks to
this contract.
Saxony, which had no executioner, also
sought his services. Reichart lived
again,
and around him, the nation too seemed to
be reborn.
The Nazis announced a plan to boost the
economy.
Like many Germans, in the summer of
1933, Johan Reichart went along with the
incredible succession of changes
happening in every field.
The press had already announced several
months earlier the creation by Guring of
the Gestapo.
Order was the priority everywhere.
Stormtroopers paraded in every town.
In 2 years, the SA expanded from 100,000
to 450,000 men. Those among them
appointed as police auxiliaries, were
now armed.
They were an instrument which made their
chief Ernst Rom, Hitler's former brother
in arms, an inescapably powerful man.
On July 14th, the NSDAP, the Nazi party,
became the only party allowed.
During the summer of 1933, Adolf Hitler
and Erns Rome could enjoy their victory.
After 10 years of political struggle,
the seeds they had planted had at last
germinated. Germany was ready to follow.
And in 8 months, most Germans had
accepted without batting an eyelid
dozens of laws and decrees that had
already fundamentally changed the
country.
For the Nazis, there remained one last
symbolic step to complete the
redisiplining of the country.
On September 21st, 1933, 9 months after
the Richtag [music] fire, began the
trial of those suspected of starting the
blaze.
>> Gobel's propaganda minister saw an
interesting opportunity to turn it into
a media platform. The great political
trial that would stand in judgment over
the plotters, communists against the
state system.
Communist
Leard.
Fore!
Foreign! Foreign!
It was a show trial. The trial was
broadcast live on radio. So, it had to
be a great moment, a great shop window
of Nazi propaganda. Except that the
trial was held according to the rules
and the defense could exercise its
rights.
As it happened, Dimmitro, one of the
accused, using his right of defense,
called two ministers to the bar as
witnesses.
Gerbles and Guring.
>> During his eight months in custody,
Dimmitrov had prepared his defense and
had scrupulously studied the German
penal code.
Guring found himself [music] in such
difficulty that Dimmitro managed to make
him lose his temper.
Feeling himself ridiculed, during had
the radio broadcast of the trial
stopped.
But from their enforced exile, anti-Nazi
German journalists loved every minute of
it.
>> This collage by the famous press artist
John Hartfield summed up the fiasco.
Only Vanderlube was found guilty while
Dimmitrov and the others were acquitted.
For the Nazis, not only was the Reichag
fire trial a crushing defeat, it showed
that the bringing to heal had not gone
to plan. The old law [music] system
still stood up against their vision of
the world. But Hitler and his lawyers
had not said their last word. And as a
reaction to the defeat they had just
suffered, they would soon put in place a
formidable strategy and new laws that
were even [music] more implacable.